Hello! Today, for the third time on my channel,
I have as SSRF vulnerability in Gitlab. This time,
however, it was found in the external component called Grafana.
It was reported by Justin Gartner and he got $12,000 for it.
Links to the report as well as to his blog post and his talk
about the topic are in the description.
Enjoy the video!
Let's start with grafana.
It's a software used for monitoring and creating graphs.
with analytics data. And it's open source, which means
it's a little bit easier to look for vulnerabilities, because
we can see the source code. And the researcher noticed the
root /avatar/:hash
where hash is the parameter. And after receiving such
requests grafana took the hash and made the request to
gravatar website.
It's used for storing avatars. The URL for this request.
Is created like this:
The first part is hard-coded and the second part is our hash.
What's important here is that the hash is everything after
the last slash of the first request, which means it includes any
parameters after the question mark. Then there is question
mark appended and value of reqParams, which are hard-coded
parameters d, size and r. So we can only control the last
part of the path and the parameters, which means that we are
far from SSRF vulnerability. Unless we can find an open
redirect vulnerability on a gravatar website and then we
could use it to redirect the server to the internal location
achieving our server site request forgery.
For this purpose a gravatar documentation about the default
URL might be very useful. The D or default parameter that
you saw earlier is used when gravatar doesn't find the image
on his own server.
It can be some predefined value like retro, but it can also
be an URL which is very promising when you're looking for
open redirects.
But when you provide the URL you get redirected to yet another domain.
This is the way that you would tell this domain where
to look for your image.
It would try to go to this location and give you back the image.
But if it would be on the domain bp.blogspot.com
instead of fetching this image for you,
It would redirect you to that domain. But you could exploit
this functionality by using bp.blogspot.com as the
path achieving an open redirect. So we can use this chain
of redirects to make the server send the request to specified
by us host.
However, there is still one problem.
There will always be that bp.blogspot.com part in the
path. But this is easy to resolve. We can just introduce yet
another redirect, this time to our server, and on our server
we can host the code that will strip this part and send the
one last open redirect to the arbitrary host and arbitrary path.
Chaining this all together the final exploit URL would
look like this:
However, if we would send it like this then grafana would
think that only this part is the hash.
So we need to remember to URL encode some values, sometimes
even more than once.
On Gitlab it was exploitable by requesting a standard AWS metadata
endpoint which usually allows to take over the whole server.
And that's it! If you're interested in more ways.
of exploiting
This grafana vulnerability, check out Justin's blog post
or his talk about the topic.
They are linked in the description, but for now, thanks for
watching. Happy hunting and goodbye!